<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Glenalmond Tea</title>
  <subtitle>by David Ochoa</subtitle>
  <id>http://glenalmondtea.org/blog</id>
  <link href="http://glenalmondtea.org/blog"/>
  <link href="http://glenalmondtea.org/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-04-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>David Ochoa</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Why start a blog (at my age)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://glenalmondtea.org/blog/2015/04/03/why_start_a_blog/"/>
    <id>http://glenalmondtea.org/blog/2015/04/03/why_start_a_blog/</id>
    <published>2015-04-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2015-04-03T22:07:01+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to explain in a brief blog post the motivations behind my decision to start this blog. For the last three or four years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reflecting on the idea of creating my own site where I could write my thoughts or explain my research in a more friendly environment. As other scientists, I had my personal website where I summarized my professional life: research interests, published articles and other merits that I thought were worth mentioning. As many others, I unsuccessfully tried to keep my &lt;a href="https://uk.linkedin.com/pub/david-ochoa/21/529/b78"&gt;LinkedIn profile&lt;/a&gt; updated, which in a sense is redundant with the personal website idea.  All this information draws a relatively flat picture of what a researcher is. In fact most of this general data about a scientist can be found without much trouble using general search engines or Pubmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Glenalmond plate" src="../../../../../images/glenalmond.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have felt the necessity to share certain thoughts or experiences that don&amp;rsquo;t fit in 140 characters. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, I truly think Twitter is a great tool to spread the knowledge — and I&amp;rsquo;ve been using &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/d0choa"&gt;my twitter account&lt;/a&gt; long enough to see skeptical scientists turn into fanatical activists of the bird cause. A very interesting article about this topic was recently published in &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7538-263a"&gt;naturejobs.com&lt;/a&gt;. However, twitter is not the best framework to give a different view to a recently published paper or to elaborate in others&amp;rsquo; research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another area I expect to comment on is events related with the scientific community. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working at the &lt;a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk"&gt;EBI&lt;/a&gt; for a year and a half during which I have experienced the scientific effervescence of the &lt;a href="https://www.sanger.ac.uk/about/campus/"&gt;Genome Campus&lt;/a&gt;. Here, it&amp;rsquo;s frequent to share conversations over a cup of coffee on research that will reach the paper in a few months. Because I think the publishing system unintentionally slows down the pace of scientific discoveries, a more active blogging will be my way to contribute to a more efficient scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the title of this post, I stress the idea of starting a blog &amp;ldquo;at my age&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;m currently 30, so not really a dinosaur in scientific terms, but it&amp;rsquo;s also true that some interesting bloggers I follow started much earlier in their careers. For example, my supervisor Pedro Beltrao has been updating his &lt;a href="http://www.evocellnet.com"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; since more than 10 years ago. I understand writing a blog might be a huge commitment and trying to feed an audience can be time-consuming. This is not my intention. I don&amp;rsquo;t promise regular updates. I will write whenever I have something to say and I will try to keep the signal to noise ratio high. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have a clear topic to write about, I see this blog as a way to share my ideas and not as something targeted for a given audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also a couple of somewhat selfish reasons why I have started this blog. As an academic career advances, more and more writing is required. Being a non-native English speaker, I sometimes find it difficult to adapt to the different registers required in scientific communication (journals, media, internet, etc.). Since I agree with the general idea that the only way to learn to write is by writing, this blog will help with that goal. Additionally, I would like to use this blog as a subtle exercise of personal branding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name of the blog took some time to decide. &lt;em&gt;Glenalmond&lt;/em&gt; refers to the name of the street where I started the blog. Pretty simple. As for tea, I recently &lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/5697622/the-hackers-guide-to-tea"&gt;read&lt;/a&gt; that the alpha wave activity observed after tea consumption is believed to play an important role in the ability to pay attention to something and avoid distraction to other stimuli.  I liked the idea of how our habits, or in this case the beverage intake, can help us keep focused. Similarly, there are many &amp;ldquo;distracting&amp;rdquo; inputs that prevent you to seat and think. I hope this blog helps me to achieve this state of scientific &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a technical point of view, I wanted a static web generator. Something simple that requires minimum maintenance and can easily be hosted.  After reading a few comparatives I finally opted by the ruby-based &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; for the engine and &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; for the hosting.  I&amp;rsquo;m particularly happy with the simplicity of the result. Now I can easily write a new post using Markdown, keep it versioned and upload the result with a couple of commands. Not a single HTML need to be changed because Middleman does it for you - awesome.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the article references, even though in my case it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a herculean effort to add them manually, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly a task I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend my time on. I opted for keeping my publications updated in &lt;a href="http://orcid.org"&gt;ORCID&lt;/a&gt; and programmatically retrieve all references using their public API. Unfortunately, I realized the amount of information available in an ORCID record depends on the resource used to claim the paper. This results in a set of incomplete and inconsistent entries that are not really helpful to build a list of references. To overcome this issue I retrieve the &lt;a href="http://www.doi.org"&gt;doi&lt;/a&gt; identifier for all my papers and resolve the reference using the combination of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ottbot/crossref"&gt;Crossref&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href="https://github.com/ottbot/crossref"&gt;BibTeX&lt;/a&gt; gems. The only problem I found so far is that requires the existence of the doi, so &lt;em&gt;advance access&lt;/em&gt; publications are not listed until they get that id. In case you feel curious the code is accessible on github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/dogcaesar/glenamondtea.org"&gt;glenalmondtea.org&lt;/a&gt;. All ideas are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
